Guide to the Richard A. Stepp Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Richard A. Stepp papers
1937-1995
SC0879
Stepp, Richard A., 1917-1995.
6 Linear feet
The papers of Richard A. Stepp pertain largely to the time he spent in Burma as an advisor on technical services for small industries, 1958-59. Included are correspondence, notebooks, reports, memos, Burmese government documents (in English), other publications, and photographs, 1954-59. Correspondents include Eugene Staley, Kennard Weddell, Edward S. Prentice, Joe E. Stepanek, and Paul J. Lovewell. A few materials in this part of the collection pertain to a small industry project he worked on in India prior to his work in Burma. The remaining personal papers, 1937-1995, include correspondence, biographical materials, family history materials, travel memorabilia, and photographs. There is a sizeable amount of correspondence with Charles Charles and his wife Anna, who were his house servants during his time in Burma, 1958-94; correspondence with and biographical materials on Charles Rozaire, Stepp?s friend and travel companion who also handled his estate matters; and several files pertaining to Stanford alumni matters and gifts to Stanford.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Richard A. Stepp earned his A.B. in social sciences at Stanford University in 1939 and his MBA in 1941. While a student he was business manager for the Stanford Daily, 1938-39, and a member of the Alpha Tau Omega fraternity. He pursued a career in real estate in Whittier, California, taught Latin American economics at USC, and was on staff at the Stanford Research Institute, 1957-59, during which time he was resident advisor to Burma?s Minister of Industries. His other interests included travel and community theater. He died in 1995.
Description of the Collection
The papers of Richard A. Stepp pertain largely to the time he spent in Burma as an advisor on technical services for small industries, 1958-59. Included are correspondence, notebooks, reports, memos, Burmese government documents (in English), other publications, and photographs, 1954-59. Correspondents include Eugene Staley, Kennard Weddell, Edward S. Prentice, Joe E. Stepanek, and Paul J. Lovewell. A few materials in this part of the collection pertain to a small industry project he worked on in India prior to his work in Burma. The remaining personal papers, 1937-1995, include correspondence, biographical materials, family history materials, travel memorabilia, and photographs. There is a sizeable amount of correspondence with Charles Charles and his wife Anna, who were his house servants during his time in Burma, 1958-94; correspondence with and biographical materials on Charles Rozaire, Stepp?s friend and travel companion who also handled his estate matters; and several files pertaining to Stanford alumni matters and gifts to Stanford.
Access Terms
Lovewell, Paul J.; Prentice, Edward S.; Rozaire, Charles E. 1927-; Staley, Eugene, 1906-1989; Stepanek, Joseph E.; Stepp, Richard A., 1917-1995.; Weddell, Kennard.; Burma--Economic conditions.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Burma itinerary and visa information 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burma residence 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Burma, RAS business cards (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Burma notebooks 1957-58 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Budgets, Burma and Pakistan projects (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Burma correspondence 1957-58 (mostly by RAS) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Burma correspondence, general 1958-60 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Burma correspondence with Ford Foundation 1958-59 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Burma – Lovewell correspondence (SRI) 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Burma – Prentice correspondence (SRI) 1958-59 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Burma – SRI correspondence 1958-59 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Burma progress reports, 1958-59 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Burma reports, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Burma Directorate of Industries, reports, memos, etc. 1957-58 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Burma Directorate of Industries, reports, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Burma industry reports by others (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Burma Proposal for the Establishment of the Small Industries Corporation, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Burma correspondence re Small Industries Corporation 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Burma Personnel Lists (Ford Foundation and others) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Burma names of firms (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Burma personnel (mostly business cards) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Burma economic conditions, notes (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Industry in Burma [newspaper in Burmese, several issues] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Burma newspaper developed by RAS (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Burma background information (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Burma background information (Ford Foundation) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Burma background information (reading lists) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Burma clippings and articles (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Burma - news clippings (in English) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Documents in Burmese (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Burma – maps (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Burma – brochures and miscellany (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Burma – invitations (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Personal effects, shipping bills for, 1957-58 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - India – Bihar Project 1954-57 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - India – reports (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Small Industry in India, report (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Small Industry in India, publications (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - International Industrial Development Conference, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - SRI memos, reports (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Articles on Laos and Vietnam (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Travel documents 1959-60 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, group 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, group 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, group 3, business related (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, group 4 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, group 5 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, group 6 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, group 7 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, group 8 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, group 9 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, group 10, business related (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, group 11 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, group 12 with negatives (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, group 13 (1961 – possibly not Burma subjects) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photographs – RAS passport image, family dog, child (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photo postcards (possibly of different Burmese peoples or tribes, some noted on back) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Burma photographs, oversized, and unsorted negatives (Box 5)
  - 1959 calendar printed on cloth, with image of Burmese textile mill (Box 5)
  - Burmese Publications
    - Language guides (Box 6)
    - Burma [Rangoon, Director of Information, Union of Burma] – Vol. 7, no. 2 The Ninth Anniversary January 1957; Vol. 8, No. 2 The Tenth Anniversary January 1958; Vol. 9 No. 2 The Eleventh Anniversary January 1959 (Box 6)
    - Economic Survey of Burma 1957 [Burmese govt. document] (Box 6)
    - Economic Survey of Burma 1958 [Burmese govt. document] (Box 6)
    - National Income of Burma; Ministry of National Planning August 1958 (Box 6)
    - Daw Khin Than Gywe, “Financing of Small Manufacturing Establishments in Burma” Economics Research Project, Dec. 1958 (Box 6)
    - Agnese N. Lockwood, “The Burma Road to Pyidawtha” International Conciliation, No. 518 May 1958 (Box 6)
    - Frank N. Trager, Helen G. Trager, “Burma Land of Golden Pagodas” Headline Series Foreign Policy Association, No. 104, March-April 1954 (Box 6)
    - Mi Mi Khaing, Burmese Family. Orient Longmans, 1956 (Box 6)
    - E. C. V. Foucar, They Reigned in Mandalay, Dennis Dobson Limited, 1946 (Box 6)
    - George Orwell, Burmese Days, Time Incorporated 1962 (Box 6)
    - Joseph E. Stepanek, Small Industry Advisory Services, An International Study, The Free Press 1960 [SRI publication] (Box 6)
    - Wil Marcus, “U.S. Private Investment and Economic Aid in Underdeveloped Countries” Public Affairs Institute, 1959 (Box 6)
    - The Burma Year-Book and Directory 1957-58 [mostly in English] (Box 7)
    - John Beamish, Burma Drop, Elek Books 1958 (Box 7)
    - Ethel Mannin, Land of the Crested Lion, A Journey Through Modern Burma, Jarrolds Publishers 1955 (Box 7)
    - Gordon S. Seagrave, Burma Surgeon, Consolidated Book Publishers, 1943 (Box 7)
    - Louis J. Walinsky, Economic Development in Burma 1951-1960, Twentieth Century Fund 1962 (Box 7)
    - The Atlantic February 1958 and Perspective of Burma, an Atlantic Month Supplement 1958 (Box 7)
    - Magazine articles on Burma, 1963-90 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles, 1958-65 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles, 1966-67 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles, 1969-71 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles, 1972-75 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles and wife Anna, 1976-82 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles, 1983-86 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles, 1987-89 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles and Anna re visit to California, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles and Anna re visit from New Delhi, 1989-90 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles and Anna, 1989-91 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Charles Charles and Anna, 1992-94 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, general, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, general, 1972-93 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, general, 1982-87 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, re trip in 1987 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, re property in Whittier, CA, 1954-72 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, between RAS and Charles Rozaire, 1976-85 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Stepp-O-Logue [annual letter], 1986 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Stepp-O-Logue [annual letter], 1987 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Stepp-O-Logue [annual letter], 1989 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Stepp-O-Logue [annual letter], 1990 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Adventurer’s Club (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Appraisal of RAS estate, Oct. 13, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Biographical clippings and information (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Community Theater work (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Driver’s license and identity card from Burma, 1958-59 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Family history – notes (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Family history – typescript (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Friends of the Daily News, Spring 1994 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Miscellany (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Obituary 1995 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Original Stanford Daily (RAS on front page), May 8, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Other ID cards, 1937, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Passports (photocopies) 1937-78 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Rotary Club of Tokyo, Weekly Report, Dec. 11, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Rozaire, Charles – biographical information (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Rozaire, Charles – holiday letters, 1981-85 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Rozaire, Charles – letter to Eric Burton re RAS affairs 1993 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Rozaire, Charles – drafts of letters re RAS last years and obituary (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Stanford University – Alumni matters (including photocopy of diploma) 1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Stanford University – Alumni giving, 1979-85 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Stanford University – gifts to, 1989-95 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Travel certificates, photocopies (many pertain to crossing the equator) (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Whittier Union High School (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Photos, Charles Charles family, 1950s (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Photos, visit of C. Charles 1989 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Photos, Charles Rozaire (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Photos, RAS in 1950s (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Photos, RAS 1980s-90s (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Photos, view from house ca. 1978 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Photos, RAS personal possessions 1978 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Photos, RAS possessions and other subjects 1989 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Photos, 1953 (catching sailfish), 1960s-70s (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Photos, 1980s-90s (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Photos, undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Photos, miscellaneous negatives (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Photos from facial surgery 1980 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Slides from facial surgery 1980 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Packet of greeting cards received (Box 11, Folder 3)